Guide to Voices of Crown Heights oral histories 2016.027
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Voices of Crown Heights oral histories: Brooklyn Movement Center, 2017; 2016.027.2
  - Porter, Evangeline, 2017 March 8; 2016.027.2.03
    Born in North Carolina in 1932 and raised there by her grandmother, Evangeline "Eve" Porter came to Brooklyn in 1953. She married at that time and lived on Sterling Street. In 1973, she moved to her own apartment on St. Charles Place. Eve Porter attended Howard University and graduated from the College of New Rochelle's School of New Resources in Brooklyn. She volunteered at her children's school, and later worked as a paraprofessional at Paul Robeson High School. Porter was a toll collector and a Passenger Service Agent at John F. Kennedy Airport; both under the aegis of the Triborough Bridge and Tunnel Authority. She also worked as a guide for builders at the construction site of the North Tower at the World Trade Center. She has been a leader of the Crow Hill Community Association for decades, oversaw an offshoot organization in 1999 called the Franklin Avenue Commercial Revitalization Project, and acted as the secretary of the 77th Precinct Community Council.
    In this interview, Evangeline "Eve" Porter vividly remembers her first trip to New York City and Brooklyn when she was nine years old; traveling to visit relatives by herself. In 1952, she recalls, she came back to Brooklyn, married, and had three children. They lived on a block of Sterling Street, with neighbors who she remembers as a cohesive unit. She speaks about what makes a good community and the values of her upbringing in North Carolina. She talks about street crime on Franklin Avenue and Crown Heights in general in the late twentieth century. Referring to Crown Heights as Crow Hill, Porter tells of her community work with the Three Saints Association. (This was the precursor to Crow Hill Community Association, which she founded.) She points out the need to include tenants in community organizing and the improvements to security via community policing and police presences as beat officers. In closing, Porter speaks to how Black people and the youth of the neighborhood interrelate, how social interactions there have improved, and the effects of having a local police captain of color. Evangeline Porter was also recorded for the Listen to this: Crown Heights Oral History collection in 2010 (2010.020). Interview conducted by Walis Johnson.
    African American neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Economic conditions |y 20th century; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions |y 20th century; Community activists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Family life -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Franklin Avenue (Brooklyn, N.Y.); Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Multiculturalism; North Carolina; Older people |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Urban renewal |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crow Hill Community Association (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Green, Roger L. (Roger Leon); Porter, Evangeline
  - Price, Carlyle, 2017 May 23; 2016.027.2.04
    Carlyle Price was born in 1980 in the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn. He grew up around Remsen and Clarkson Avenues, technically outside the borders of the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn, but spent most of his time in Crown Heights. His parents, Clifton Carlyle Price and Pearleta Price, (also a narrator in this series) were born in Barbados. He has two siblings, as well as many extended relatives. He went to many different schools, including PS 219 and PS 115 in Brooklyn, St. Bernard's School for Boys in the Upper East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, Berkeley Carroll School in Brooklyn, and then— for higher education— Swarthmore College in Pennsylvania, and Brooklyn College, where he completed a degree in Linguistics. He also spent a year studying linguistic anthropology in France. For a few years, he worked as a bookseller at Barnes and Noble, and also provided tutoring and other educational assistance for youth. In 2012, he acquired an internship at the State Assembly in Albany. Price currently works for the Urban Homesteading Assistance Board as the lead organizer for the Crown Heights Tenant Union.
    In this interview, Carlyle Price discusses his atypical childhood, largely through a lens of his schooling. He recalls the challenges he faced throughout his educational experiences as a Black man. Price reflects on being racially profiled and other interactions with police. He remembers the importance of learning Black history as a child, and considers themes of Black consciousness and aspiration. Talking about gentrification, Price identifies the social cost of disappearing storefronts and links to ideas of belonging, home, familiarity and community. He analyzes safety by gauging if there's a sense of freedom and the ability to play in a neighborhood. He also shares his feelings on racially-charged controversies in New York City's past, specifically Gavin Cato's death in Crown Heights and the Central Park Five. In closing, Price voices his frustration with unfair public transit, and details his fight for justice in a domestic violence charge in Albany. Interview conducted by Jenny Goldberg.
    African American neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Albany (N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Economic conditions; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Canarsie (New York, N.Y.); Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Children |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community activists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Family life -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Multiculturalism; New York (N.Y.); Parents |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Police-community relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Private schools; Race relations |z United States; Racism |z New York (State) |z New York; Urban renewal |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Cato, Gavin; Crown Heights Tenant Union (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); New York (N.Y.). Police Department; Price, Carlyle; St. Bernard's School (Manhattan, New York, N.Y.); St. Paul's School (Concord, N.H.)
  - Price, Pearleta, 2017 March 24; 2016.027.2.05
    Pearleta Price was born in Christchurch, Barbados in 1952. She grew up on a farm and was one of ten siblings. When she was sixteen, her family moved to Brooklyn— 136 Rockaway Parkway— and she enrolled in George H. Wingate High School in the Prospect Lefferts Gardens neighborhood of Brooklyn. She attended Hunter College and Medgar Evers College, where she earned two bachelor's degrees in education and Liberal Studies: Geography. For many years, she was an elementary and middle school teacher at various schools throughout Brooklyn, where she taught math and English Language Arts. She also worked as a paraprofessional for the Board of Education. She then worked as a make-up artist on Broadway; working on The Color Purple and Dreamgirls, and in 2017, she worked primarily as a make-up artist for the musical,Phantom of the Opera. She continues to work as a teacher on a freelance basis. She is the mother to three children; Carlyle, Bryan, and Grace. She currently lives on Clarkson Avenue between East 92nd and 93rd Streets.
    In the interview, Pearleta Price begins with reflections on growing up in Barbados. She talks about her work as a Broadway make-up artist. Price recalls early days in Brooklyn; in 1968, at sixteen, she moved with her family to the Crown Heights neighborhood, during a harsh winter. She describes being the only Black family on the block (136 Rockaway Parkway) and her predominantly Jewish neighbors. She compares her education in Barbados with that of George H. Wingate High School. Many changes in the neighborhood are described; with a focus on mom and pop stores being replaced by more anonymous larger stores. Price talks about her church attendance and how the family's churches intersected with community support of tenants' rights. She remembers several factors related to the August 1991 turmoil in Crown Heights. Price ends with a discussion of West Indian Carnival and her criticism of how it has evolved. Interview conducted by Jenny Goldberg.
    Barbados; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community organizing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Gangs |z New York (State) |z Kings Country; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jewish neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jews |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Parents |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Police-community relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Riots |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Theater |z New York (State) |z New York; Cato, Gavin; New York (N.Y.). Police Department; Price, Carlyle; Price, Pearleta; Rosenbaum, Yankel; West Indian American Day Carnival Parade (Brooklyn, N.Y.)
  - Sidof, Yocheved, 2017 March 27; 2016.027.2.06
    Thirty-eight years old at the time of the 2017 interview, Yocheved Sidof is a Hasidic woman who was born in Minnesota. She is the daughter of Iranian Jewish immigrants and was raised in a very insular Hasidic community. Sidof has a bachelor's degree in psychology. She is the Executive Director of the Lamplighters Yeshiva, a Montessori progressive school in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn. Married and a mother of three daughters and a son, she moved to New York City in 1997 when she was seventeen years old. While attending Yeshiva University, she resided in Crown Heights on a short-term basis. She returned there after graduation, and has been a part of the community on a nearly consistent basis since.
    In the interview, Yocheved Sidof begins with reflections on growing up in Minnesota, attending an out-of-state boarding school in her teens, and coming to New York City for Yeshiva University. She talks about the Hasidic community of her youth and within the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn. Sidof recalls her early experiences with that part of Brooklyn and evaluates the lifestyles, spiritual energy, and social mores that made it a dynamic locale for her. With an anecdote about her car being stolen, she links to general concerns and community efforts related to policing and safety. She relates her own progress in life— relationships and career choices— with how Crown Heights became less, then more important for her. Sidof talks about her filmmaking and photography efforts that she used to draw out profiles of people and the community of Crown Heights. She describes how she began a family and their efforts at finding a home. Sidof also relates the origin and progress of the Lamplighters school. In closing, she observes how gentrification has changed the area, and reflects on the ever-evolving sense of community and safety in Crown Heights. Interview conducted by Walis Johnson.
    African Americans |x Relations with Jews; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Community development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Education |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jewish neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jews, American |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Multiculturalism; Parents |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Police-community relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Private schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Religious identity; Saint Paul (Minn.); Lamplighters Yeshivah (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Sidof, Yocheved; Stern College for Women
  - Staton, Meredith and Staton, Lula, 2017 March 28; 2016.027.2.07
    Meredith Staton was born in Germantown, Pennsylvania in 1938. He moved to the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn in his twenties. Staton served his country in the Vietnam War and as a United States Postal Service employee at home. He has been the Captain of the Auxiliary Police Unit for the 77th Precinct and served on Community Board Eight. He retired from policing in 2010 due to a stroke. Vocal in the past on how the community reacted to the Atlantic Yards project and how Crown Heights was redistricted, more recently he was a proponent of securing landmark status for features of the neighborhood. With his wife, Lula Stanton, he raised three children; one of whom was recently deceased at the time of the 2017 interview.
    In the interview, Meredith Staton begins with an explanation of the redistricting of the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn into North and South. In a few instances throughout, he uses the distribution of the city's homeless shelters as an example of social inequity. Staton and his wife, Lula, reflect on how they bought their house from the last White family on the block in 1963. That leads into a discussion of how people feel "pushed out" because housing prices are so high. The couple describes the turn from a quiet neighborhood to one struggling with crime issues emanating from nearby public housing. Staton describes his experience with the police department and leading a group of patrolling volunteers, and the associated social benefits with safety. The couple refers to the precipitating events and the unrest of Crown Heights in August of 1991. They emphasize community safety and policing again, and Staton weighs in on the stop-and-frisk method. Meredith Staton was also recorded for the Listen to this: Crown Heights Oral History collection in 2010 (2010.020). Interview conducted by Walis Johnson.
    African Americans |x Relations with Jews; African Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Blacks |x Race identity; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Community activists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Older people |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Parents |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Police-community relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Riots |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Cato, Gavin; Community Board No. 8 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Community Board No. 9 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Staton, Lula; Staton, Meredith
  - Zimmerman, Rusty, 2017 March 9; 2016.027.2.08
    Rusty Zimmerman, thirty-eight at the time of the interview, is a White male who was born in Englewood, New Jersey. He and his family moved often during his early years, but Zimmerman relocated to New York City in 2005 in order to establish his trade as a freelance illustrator and painter. In 2009, he moved to the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn, and in an attempt to further hone his craft and engage his community, he began the Free Portrait Project in 2015, in which he interviewed and painted portraits of over 200 residents in Crown Heights over the course of one year. The culmination of the project was a series of exhibitions and community events, and Zimmerman received grant funding to edit and distribute the 900 hours of audio interviews he recorded while conducting the four-hour portrait sessions with each of his subjects.
    In this interview, Randy Zimmerman discusses his personal background as well as the impetus for and timeline of his Free Portrait Project. He describes a typical portrait session, and some of the things he learned while doing this work. He shares anecdotes about several of the people he met throughout the process, and how he has become a liaison of sorts between disparate parts of the community. Through his network of community members he has found the goal of encouraging his neighbors to find commonalities where they assume there are only differences. Zimmerman speaks openly and candidly about the preconceived notions and prejudices that we all carry within us, and how his work on the Free Portrait Project has helped him accept and freely admit to those perceptions in a hope of openly and honestly grappling with them. Lastly, he talks about his personal experiences with the police and the 77th precinct, his run-ins with the police, and his realization of his "White privilege" during those moments, and his perceptions about what could be done to further improve community relations. Interview conducted by Candace Thompson.
    Activism; African Americans |x Relations with Jews; Art |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Artists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Community activists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community organizing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Multiculturalism; Neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Police-community relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Racism |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Congregation Lubavitch (Crown Heights, New York, N.Y.); Free Portrait Project (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); New York (N.Y.). Police Department; Zimmerman, Rusty
- Voices of Crown Heights oral histories: Weeksville Heritage Center, 2017; 2016.027.3
  - Alexander, Deborah, 2017 January 9; 2016.027.3.01
    Aged fifty-five at the time of the 2017 interview, Deborah Alexander grew up in the Bronx, with her family originally being from the American South. She attended Ithaca College and got her master's degree at Brooklyn College. Alexander is a speech teacher at PS 243 (The Weeksville School) in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn. She lives in that area, having raised a son and daughter who were both adults by the time of the interview.
    In this interview, Deborah Alexander talks about her life growing up in the Bronx and what led her to eventually become a speech teacher in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn. She discusses her experiences in Intelligent and Gifted Classes (IGC) in both junior high school and Lehman High School. She recalls facing racism in an incident at school that corresponded with the Roots series' premiere. She describes her role in the Afro-Latin Club at Ithaca College and the racism that she also faced there as a student. She delves into her experiences as a speech teacher and the reemergence of the Weeksville Museum at PS 243. Alexander then evaluates the differences between her life as a student and the lives of students circa 2017. Interview conducted by Obden Mondésir.
    African American neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Bronx (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Charter schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community identity |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Education |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Exhibitions; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Intergenerational relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Parents |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Public schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; School children |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Teachers |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Alexander, Deborah, 1961-; Derico, Jean L.; Jarvis, Cleo; P.S. 243 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Society for the Preservation of Weeksville and Bedford-Stuyvesant History; Weeksville Parent-Teacher Association (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
  - Britt, Morris, 2017 January 10; 2016.027.3.02
    Morris Britt is a sixty-three year old man, originally from St. George, South Carolina. In 1970, after finishing high school, he moved to New York in hopes of finding work and eventually found himself working as a janitor at PS 243. Married and a father of a son and daughter, he remained employed at the Weeksville School at the time of this 2017 interview.
    In this interview, Morris Britt recalls that he moved to New York because of the racism in the South and his realization that he could not "exist" in South Carolina. He talks about living in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn since 1970 and how he found himself working as a janitor at the Weeksville School at eighteen years old. Britt recounts how PS 243 changed its name from the Isaac Newton School to the Weeksville School. He discusses the politically and culturally involved faculty members that worked at the school, such as Marguerite Thompson, Joyce Washington, and Parent-Teacher Association president Elman Meggs. Britt reviews how the school and neighborhood have changed from 1970-2017, touching on what it was like to have his son attend the school. He also considers his first dealings with gentrification. Interview conducted by Obden Mondésir.
    African American neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Charter schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community identity |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Education |z New York (State) |z New York; Exhibitions; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Public schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; School children |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Teachers |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Britt, Morris; Butler, Herman; Derico, Jean L.; P.S. 243 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Washington, Joyce
  - Brown Green, Myrah, 2017 February 7; 2016.027.3.03
    Sixty years old at the time of the 2017 interview, Dr. Myrah Brown Green is a Black woman originally from Cambridge, Massachusetts and a longtime resident of the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn. She moved to New York to attend Pratt Institute for a master in fashion merchandizing and found work at Lord and Taylor. While at this job, she met Richard Green, a community organizer. They married after moving to Brooklyn. Displeased with the options of private school or PS 241, they eventually decided to homeschool their four children. She then became the principal of their newly formed "home school" which they named the Crown Heights Collective Fellowship and Peace Academy.